<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Jinsong Zhang</title>
    <link>https://zhangj5.github.io/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://zhangj5.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Jinsong Zhang {2022}</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://zhangj5.github.io/images/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>https://zhangj5.github.io/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simultaneous detection and quantification of leukemia fusion gene isoforms from RNA-Seq data in AML</title>
      <link>https://zhangj5.github.io/post/simultaneous-detection-and-quantification-of-leukemia-fusion-genes-in-aml/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zhangj5.github.io/post/simultaneous-detection-and-quantification-of-leukemia-fusion-genes-in-aml/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction-and-objective&#34;&gt;Introduction and objective&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the earliest fusion genes discovered in the history of biomedical science is a fusion between the BCR gene and the ABL gene. This creates the fusion protein BCR-ABL, which is the cause of a common type of leukemia known as t(9;22) CML.
&lt;img src=&#34;https://nci-media.cancer.gov/pdq/media/images/533336.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Chromosomal translocation between BCR and ABL gene&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since then, many different leukemia fusion proteins have been reported and shown to act as drivers in various leukemias. One of these is AML1-ETO, which arises from the chromosomal translocation t(8;21) and is responsible for 10-15% of all cases of acute myeloid leukemia (AML). While AML tends to affect older patients, t(8;21) AML appears to affect children and young adults more frequently. At the molecular level, AML1-ETO is an in-frame fusion between the DNA-binding domain of the AML/RUNX1 gene and most of the ETO/MTG8/RUNX1T1 protein, missing a small portion of the N-terminus, which is a non-conserved sequence in ETO family proteins. At the DNA level, a fusion occurs between intron 3 of RUNX1 and intron 1 of ETO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./9a_location.png&#34; alt=&#34;Expression of exon 9a in an t(8;21) AML detected by RNA-Seq and location of the t(8;21) translocation site&#34; width=&#34;748&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Figure 1: Expression of exon 9a in an t(8;21) AML detected by RNA-Seq and location of the t(8;21) translocation site&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;./runx1_location.png&#34; alt=&#34;The marked sequence and its upstream region are translocated into the ETO gene in t(8;21) AML&#34; width=&#34;748&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Figure 2: The marked sequence and its upstream region are translocated into the ETO gene in t(8;21) AML&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are 12 exons for the ETO gene in the official human reference genome. However, Dr. Dong-Er Zhang found that one unannotated exon is transcribed to generate an alternative splice variant of AML1-ETO. This exon was designated exon 9a and the corresponding AML1-ETO variant was designated AML1-ETO9a (&lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/nm1443&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Yan, M., Kanbe, E., Peterson, L. et al. A previously unidentified alternatively spliced isoform of t(8;21) transcript promotes leukemogenesis. Nat Med 12, 945-949 (2006)&lt;/a&gt;). While full-length AML1-ETO has 752 amino acids, AML1-ETO9a has only 542 amino acids. This is because exon 9a, if retained after splicing, would introduce a premature stop codon in frame.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the protein level, AML1-ETO9a lacks a C-terminal sequence that is present in the full-length protein. This sequence has been shown to interact with proteins involved in transcriptional repression. It is not yet known whether the amount of AML1-ETO9a has an impact on disease progression. One way to address this question is to compare the prognosis of patients who have high or low levels of AML1-ETO9a at diagnosis. However, the results are controversial. While early studies suggested that AML1-ETO9a expression was associated with poor prognosis in t(8;21) AML [ref], a recent work by Agrawal M et al &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038%2Fs41375-019-0551-4&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Functional and clinical characterization of the alternatively spliced isoform AML1-ETO9a in adult patients with translocation t(8;21)(q22;q22.1) acute myeloid leukemia (AML). Leukemia. 2020 Feb;34(2):630-634&lt;/a&gt; showed that the level of AML1-ETO9a did not affect prognosis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another possibility is that AML1-ETO9a expression, although not a prognostic factor at diagnosis, increases after treatment in a manner that promotes disease progression. In this case, we would expect AML1-ETO9a expression to be increased in relapsed AML.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this study is to develop an algorithm to detect the fusion genes using RNA-Seq data and quantify the expression of their isoforms. For the above reasons, we focused on the AML1-ETO isoforms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;methods&#34;&gt;Methods&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We used the &lt;a href=&#34;https://pachterlab.github.io/kallisto/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Kallisto&lt;/a&gt;software to quantify transcript levels. Kallisto quantifies the expression of a given transcript by aligning the reads to a transcriptomic index created from the sequences of available transcripts in the genome. In our case, we created a custom index by replacing the ETO/RUNX1T1 isoforms with the sequences of FL AML1-ETO and AML1-ETO9a. The RNA-Seq of the patient samples were downloaded from the NCI TARGET AML database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;results&#34;&gt;Results&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;expression-of-aml1-eto9a-is-detected-in-all-amls-with-known-t821-status-and-some-amls-with-unknown-or-nagative-t821-status&#34;&gt;Expression of AML1-ETO9a is detected in all AMLs with known t(8;21) status and some AMLs with unknown or nagative t(8;21) status.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://zhangj5.github.io/post/simultaneous-detection-and-quantification-of-leukemia-fusion-genes-in-aml/index.en_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-4-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Expression of AML1-ETO FL and AML1-ETO9a&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Figure 3: Expression of AML1-ETO FL and AML1-ETO9a&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, we found that AML1-ETO9a was expressed in non-t(8;21) AMLs, including AMLs with &amp;ldquo;unknown&amp;rdquo; t(8;21) status and AMLs with negative t(8;21) status, as determined by assays such as FISH. One possibility is that these assays were not sensitive enough to detect the presence of fusion genes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;detection-of-aml1-eto-fusion-transcripts-by-star-fusion-and-kallisto-fusion-tools&#34;&gt;Detection of AML1-ETO fusion transcripts by STAR-fusion and Kallisto-fusion tools.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some algorithms have been developed to detect fusion genes based on RNA-Seq data. We tested two such algorithms, including STAR -fusion and Kallisto-fusion. Both algorithms found that the two AMLs with an &amp;ldquo;unknown&amp;rdquo; t(8;21) status but expressing high levels of AML1-ETO9a indeed had fusion between AML1 and ETO. Interestingly, the Kallisto- fusion found that several AMLs with negative t(8;21) status but expressing detectable levels of AML1-ETO also contained AML1-ETO fusion transcripts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://zhangj5.github.io/post/simultaneous-detection-and-quantification-of-leukemia-fusion-genes-in-aml/index.en_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-6-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Detection of AML1-ETO fusion by STAR-Fusion&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Figure 4: Detection of AML1-ETO fusion by STAR-Fusion&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://zhangj5.github.io/post/simultaneous-detection-and-quantification-of-leukemia-fusion-genes-in-aml/index.en_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-7-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;Detection of AML1-ETO fusion by Kallisto-Fusion&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Figure 5: Detection of AML1-ETO fusion by Kallisto-Fusion&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;aml1-eto9a-expression-at-the-time-of-diagnosis-was-not-correlated-with-disease-progression&#34;&gt;AML1-ETO9a expression at the time of diagnosis was not correlated with disease progression.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://zhangj5.github.io/post/simultaneous-detection-and-quantification-of-leukemia-fusion-genes-in-aml/index.en_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-8-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;AML1-ETO9a levels at diagnosis cannot predict patient outcome&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Figure 6: AML1-ETO9a levels at diagnosis cannot predict patient outcome&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
### AML1-ETO9a levels are significantly elevated in t(8;21) AML in relapse.
&lt;p&gt;Since we have now determined AML1-ETO9a levels at both diagnosis and relapse, we wanted to know whether its expression changed significantly at relapse compared with diagnosis. This required the use of paired AMLs, for which 5 cases were available for t(8;21) AML.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;https://zhangj5.github.io/post/simultaneous-detection-and-quantification-of-leukemia-fusion-genes-in-aml/index.en_files/figure-html/unnamed-chunk-9-1.png&#34; alt=&#34;AML1-ETO9a is significantly increased at relape in t(8;21) AML&#34; width=&#34;672&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Figure 7: AML1-ETO9a is significantly increased at relape in t(8;21) AML&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The results showed that the expression of AML1-ETO9a significantly increased in t(8;21) AML at relapse. This suggests a role for AML1-ETO9a in promoting disease progression in t(8;21) AML.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;a-kallisto-based-algorithm-fusionquant-has-been-developed-to-simantaneouly-detect-and-quantify-leukemia-fusion-genes&#34;&gt;A Kallisto-based algorithm (FusionQuant) has been developed to simantaneouly detect and quantify leukemia fusion genes.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;aml1-eto9a-levels-at-the-time-of-diagnosis-do-not-correlate-with-survival&#34;&gt;AML1-ETO9a levels at the time of diagnosis do not correlate with survival.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;aml1-eto9a-levels-are-significantly-increased-in-relapsed-amls-suggesting-a-role-for-aml1-eto9-in-disease-progression&#34;&gt;AML1-ETO9a levels are significantly increased in relapsed AMLs, suggesting a role for AML1-ETO9 in disease progression.&lt;/h3&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recent COVID-19 Outbreak in China</title>
      <link>https://zhangj5.github.io/post/recent-covid19-outbreak-in-china/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zhangj5.github.io/post/recent-covid19-outbreak-in-china/</guid>
      <description>&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://zhangj5.shinyapps.io/COVID19/&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;800px&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the relationship between gene expression and leukemia prognosis in Shiny</title>
      <link>https://zhangj5.github.io/post/exploring-leukemia-prognosis-using-in-shiny/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://zhangj5.github.io/post/exploring-leukemia-prognosis-using-in-shiny/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The acute myeloid leukemia (AML) is one of the most devastating forms of cancer. AML prognosis is determined by many factors. Here, we build a dynamic application in Shiny to explore the relationship between patient prognosis and gene expression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe src=&#34;https://zhangj5.shinyapps.io/Acute_Myeloid_Leukemia_Prognosis/&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;800px&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
